Guide to the Edgar Saltus Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edgar Saltus papers
1884-1926
YCAL MSS 425
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.02
(12 boxes) + 1 broadside
The Edgar Saltus papers contain writings, correspondence, and other materials documenting the life of American author Edgar Saltus.
Saltus, Edgar, 1855-1921
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elsie Saltus Munds, 1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Edgar Saltus (1855-1921)
Edgar Saltus was a novelist, essayist, and poet. He attended St. Paul's School in Concord, New Hampshire and Yale College in 1876 and 1877, before studying abroad and receiving the degree of LL.B. from Columbia College in 1880, though he never practiced law. Saltus was married three times: to Helen Sturgis Read in November 1883, to Elsie Welch Smith on October 8, 1895, and to author Marie Florence Giles on August 16, 1911. There is considerable scholarship on Saltus, including book-length biographical studies by Marie Saltus (1925) and Claire Sprague (1968). Summary information is available in the standard biographical resources.
Scope and Contents
The Edgar Saltus papers contain writings, correspondence, and other materials documenting the life and work of author Edgar Saltus. Writings consist chiefly of drafts, some heavily corrected, for shorter works such as poems, stories, and essays, but include substantive drafts for the novels The Ghost Girl (1922) and The Paliser Case (1919) and other longer works. Correspondence consists of a small number of letters between Saltus and family members, publishers, editors, and other writers, most notably James Huneker and Richard Le Gallienne, and British actor Henry Irving. Other materials include three scrapbooks containing clippings, with reviews and writings, printed ephemera, photographs, and correspondence relating to Saltus, his family, and his third wife, author Marie Florence Giles.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Writings, 1884-1919. II. Correspondence, 1888-1925. Other Materials, 1889-1926.
American literature -- 19th century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- Archives; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographic prints; Scrapbooks; Authors; Giles, Marie Florence, 1883?-1960; Huneker, James, 1857-1921; Irving, H. B. (Henry Brodribb), 1870-1919; Le Gallienne, Richard, 1866-1947; Saltus, Edgar, 1855-1921
- Writings, 1884-1919; Series I; 3.13; (8 boxes) + 1 broadside
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title or supplied heading.
  Series I, Writings, consists of drafts for shorter works, such as poems, stories, and essays, and for novels, The Ghost Girl (1922) and The Paliser Case (1919), and other longer works. Most drafts are hand-written (holograph) and signed, and some are heavily corrected. In addition to the genre, the presence of multiple drafts and other physical formats (typescript or clippings) is noted in folder headings below. A small number of notebooks are filed by title.
  Additional short writings can be found among the clippings in scrapbooks in Series III. Other Materials.
  - "After the Ball," play, drafts, 1913; 2 (Box 1)
  - "Around the Clock," story, drafts, undated (Box 1)
  - "Around the Town," essay, drafts, undated (Box 1)
  - "Barbey d'Aurevilly," story, 1919 February (Box 1)
  - "The Beloved," story, undated (Box 1)
  - "Bonbons and Burgundy," essay, undated (Box 1)
  - "The Brute," story, drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "The Club Window," essay, drafts, undated (Box 1)
  - "The Cupboard," story, undated (Box 1)
  - "The Crime's Third Anniversary," essay, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1)
  - "The Dangers of Health," essay, drafts, typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "De omnibus rebus e...," notebook, notes, poems, drafts, 1896 March (Box 1)
  - "Dinner is Served," story, undated (Box 1)
  - "Done up Brown," story, undated (Box 1)
  - "Fashion," essay, draft fragments, undated (Box 1)
  - "The Gates of Life," play, typescript carbon, corrected, 1910 (Box 2)
  - "The Ghost," story, drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - The Ghost Girl, novel, typescript, corrected, [circa 1922] (Box 2)
  - "The Goblin Girl," story, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Golden Chimera," essay, undated (Box 2)
  - 'The Golden Flood," novel, drafts, undated (Box 3)
  - "Golgotha," essay, drafts, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Halls of Elbis," novel, drafts, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Happiest Way," essay, drafts, undated (Box 3)
  - "Here," poem, undated (Box 3)
  - Historia Amorus, title page and table of contents, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Horrors of Grub Street," essay, drafts, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Hue and Cry," story, drafts, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - The Imperial Orgy, draft fragments, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Impostor," play scenario, [circa 1894] (Box 4)
  - "Jewels," poem, undated (Box 4)
  - "Jonathan Club Is 'Original as Well as Unique'," article, printed version, Los Angeles Examiner, 1909 November 15 (Box 12 (Broadside))
  - "The Lords of the Ghostland: A History of the Ideal," essay, drafts, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Loveland," story, drafts, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Man Who Did Not Exist," story, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Metropolitan Opera Glass," essay, drafts, [1899 August?] (Box 4)
  - "Mrs. Cornelius Vanderbilt," essay, undated (Box 4)
  - "Myosotis and Opals," essay, undated (Box 5)
  - "The Mystery of Love," essay, undated (Box 5)
  - "The New Paganism," essay, undated (Box 5)
  - "Not Yet," essay, typescript carbon, undated (Box 5)
  - "Nuptials," poem, drafts, undated (Box 5)
  - "The Origin of the Crime," essay, drafts, undated (Box 5)
  - Oscar Wilde: An Idler's Impression, essay, drafts, [1916?] (Box 5)
  - The Paliser Case, novel, drafts, [circa 1919]; 2 (Box 5)
  - Parnassians Persmally Encountered, story, drafts, undated (Box 5)
  - "Peace," poem, drafts, undated (Box 5)
  - The Perfume of Eros, novel, drafts (incomplete), [circa 1905] (Box 6)
  - "The Pipes of Priapus," essay, undated (Box 6)
  - "The Pomps of Fashion," essay, undated (Box 6)
  - "Poppies and Mandragora, Allegresse," poem, drafts, undated (Box 6)
  - "The Punch," story, drafts, undated (Box 6)
  - "The Reflections of Floriline Schopenhauer on Perfumes, as Dictated to Edgar Saltus," story, drafts, undated (Box 6)
  - "The Rogues Gallery," essay, drafts, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - "Rome," notebook, notes, early drafts, 1891 (Box 6)
  - "The Russian Miracle," essay, drafts, undated (Box 6)
  - "Scaffolds and Altars," table of contents and draft fragments, undated (Box 6)
  - "Silver Bullets," essay, typescript carbon, undated (Box 6)
  - "The Singer the Sorcerer and the Secrets of Satanism," article, printed version, New York Herald, 1903 February 1 (Box 12 (Broadside))
  - "Sonnets Serene and Otherwise," notebook, [1884-1885] (Box 7)
  - "The Soul of the World," essay, drafts, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Stage," essay, draft fragments, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Sultan's Daughter," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "Sunday Matter," galley proof, fragment, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Terrible Wedding," story and play, drafts, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - "Teuton Illusions," essay, typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "That Girl," story, drafts, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - "That Woman," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "A Tragedy of Real Life in New York," article, printed version, The Journal, 1896 April 26 (Box 12 (Broadside))
  - The Tsars: From the First to the Last, clippings and typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Valley of Paradise," play, typescript, undated (Box 7)
  - "Victor Hugo," essay, clippings and typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Von Altmont," story, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Wager," story, drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - "Wall Street," essay, undated (Box 7)
  - "William the Peacemaker," essay, undated (Box 7)
  - Other writings, 1898-1899, undated (Box 8)
- Correspondence, 1888-1925; Series II; 0.11; (10 folders)
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series II, Correspondence, contains a small number of letters between Edgar Saltus and family members, publishers, editors, and other writers, most notably James Huneker and Richard Le Gallienne, and British actor Henry Irving. Additional correspondence to Saltus and his wife Marie Florence Giles can be found in the scrapbooks in Series III. Other Materials.
  - Boni & Liveright, 1919, undated (Box 9)
  - Gilliams, E. Leslie, undated (Box 9)
  - Greening & Co. Ltd., 1901 April 26 (Box 9)
  - Huneker, James, [1916-1920], undated (Box 9)
  - Irving, H. B. (Henry Brodribb), 1918 October 17 (Box 9)
  - Le Gallienne, Richard, undated (Box 9)
  - Lifland, S., 1918 December 26 (Box 9)
  - Munds, Elsie Saltus, undated (Box 9)
  - The Sun, undated (Box 9)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 9)
- Other Materials, 1889-1926; Series III; 0.1; (4 folders)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III, Other Materials, contains a single manuscript fragment, photograph of Edgar Fawcett, will, and three scrapbooks. The scrapbooks contain clippings, printed ephemera, photographs, and correspondence. The clippings relate to Saltus, his wife Marie Giles, and family, and include reviews and writings. Writings, for example, include printed versions of poems, short fiction, and essays for such magazines as Harper's Bazaar, as well as a number of short pieces for newspapers dating from 1902 and 1903.
  - Manuscript fragment, undated (Box 9)
  - Photograph of Edgar Fawcett, 1889 March
  - Printed ephemera, undated (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks, 1898-1926, undated
  - Stationery, undated (Box 9)
  - Will, draft, 1903 June 10 (Box 9)
- Oversize, 4; (3 boxes)
  - Empty cases, undated (Box 13 (Oversize))
  - Photograph of Edgar Fawcett, 1889 March (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbook, 1898-1926, undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbook, 1902-1908, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbook, 1912-1914, undated (Box 11 (Oversize))